Session 11 Assignment

1. The time required for servicing transmissions is normally distributed with   = 45 minutes and   = 8minutes. The service manager plans to have work begin on the transmission of a customer’s car 10 minutes after the car is dropped off  and  the customer is told that the car will be ready within 1 hour from drop-off. What is the probability that the service manager cannot  meet his commitment?

Ans- We have a normal distribution with   = 45 and   = 8.0. Let X  be the amount of time it takes to complete the repair on a customer's car. To finish in one hour you must have X ≤ 50 so the question is to find Pr(X > 50).
Pr(X > 50) = 1 - Pr(X ≤ 50).
Z = (X -  )/  = (X - 45)/8.0
Thus the question can be answered by using the normal table to find
Pr(X ≤ 50) = Pr(Z ≤ (50 - 45)/8.0) = Pr(Z ≤ 0.625)=73.4%
Probability that the service manager will not meet his demand will be = 100-73.4 = 26.6% or 0.2676

2. The current age (in years) of 400 clerical employees at an insurance claims processing center is normally distributed with mean    = 38 and Standard deviation   = 6. For each statement below, please specify True/False. If false, briefly explain why.
A. More employees at the processing center are older than 44 than between 38 and 44.
B. A training program for employees under the age of 30 at the center would be expected to attract about 36 employees.

Ans - We have a normal distribution with   = 38 and   = 6. Let X be the number of employees. So according to question
a)Probabilty of employees greater than age of 44= Pr(X>44)
Pr(X > 44) = 1 - Pr(X ≤ 44).
Z = (X -  )/  = (X - 38)/6
Thus the question can be answered by using the normal table to find
Pr(X ≤ 44) = Pr(Z ≤ (44 - 38)/6) = Pr(Z ≤ 1)=84.1345%
Probabilty that the employee will be greater than age of 44 = 100-84.1345=15.86%
 So the probability of number of employees between 38-44 years of age = Pr(X<44)-0.5=84.1345-0.5= 34.1345%
Therefore the statement  that “More employees at the processing center are older than 44 than between 38 and 44” is TRUE.
b) Probabilty of employees less than age of 30 =  Pr(X<30).
Z = (X -  )/  = (30 - 38)/6
Thus the  question can be answered by using the normal table to find
Pr(X ≤ 30) = Pr(Z ≤ (30 - 38)/6) = Pr(Z ≤ -1.333)=9.12%
So the number of employees with probability 0.912 of them being under age 30 = 0.0912*400=36.48( or 36 employees).
Therefore the statement B of the question is also TRUE.

3. If X1 ~ N(μ, σ^2) and X2 ~ N(μ, σ^2) are iid normal random variables, then what is the difference between  2 X1 and X1 + X2? Discuss both their distributions and parameters.

Ans- As we know that if  X ∼ N(µ1, σ1^2 ), and  Y ∼ N(µ2, σ2^2 ) are two independent  random variables then   X + Y ∼ N(µ1 + µ2, σ1^2 + σ2^2 ) , and      X − Y ∼ N(µ1 − µ2, σ1^2 + σ2^2 ) .
Similarly if  Z = aX + bY , where X and Y are as defined above, i.e Z is linear combination of X and Y , then Z ∼ N(aµ1 + bµ2, a^2σ1^2 + b^2σ2^2 ).
Therefore in the question 
2X1~ N(2 u,4 σ^2) and 
X1+X2 ~  N(µ + µ, σ^2 + σ^2 ) ~ N(2 u, 2σ^2 )
2X1-(X1+X2) = N( 4µ,6 σ^2)

4. Let X ~ N(100, 202) , Find two values, a and b, symmetric about the mean, such that the probability of the random variable taking a value between them is 0.99.

Ans. Since we need to find out the values of a and b, which are symmetric about the mean, such that the probability of random variable taking a value between them is 0.99, we have to work out in reverse order. 
The Probability of getting value between a and b should be 0.99.
So the Probability of going wrong, or the Probability outside the a and b area is 0.01 (ie. 1-0.99).
The Probability towards left from a = -0.005 (ie. 0.01/2). 
The Probability towards right from b = +0.005 (ie. 0.01/2).
So since we have the probabilities of a and b, we need to calculate X, the random variable at a and b which has got these probabilities. 
By finding the Standard Normal Variable Z (Z Value), we can calculate the X values.
Z=(X- μ) / σ 
For Probability 0.005 the Z Value is -2.57 (from Z Table).
Z * σ + μ = X
Z(-0.005)*20+100 = -(-2.57)*20+100 = 151.4
Z(+0.005)*20+100 = (-2.57)*20+100 = 48.6
So, option D is correct.

